Guide to the Heather Lewis Papers 1965-2002 (Bulk 1980-1999) MSS 132 MSS.132
Fales Library and Special Collections
Heather Lewis Papers
ca. 1965-2002
Fales Library and Special Collections
MSS.132
13 Linear Feet (15 boxes)
The Heather Lewis Papers reflect Heather Lewis's writing career including her manuscripts, publishing contracts, correspondence and financial information. In addition, the collection includes a great deal of information relating to Heather Lewis's personal life including journals, photographs, and personal correspondence. The collection reflects the connections between Lewis's career as a writer and her personal life and presents the author as a complex whole.
Provenance
Ann Rower donated The Heather Lewis Papers to the Fales Library and Special Collections in January 2003.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Biographical Note
Heather Lewis was born in Bedford, New York and attended Sarah Lawrence College. She is the author of three published novels. The first, House Rules (1994), details the experiences of a fifteen year old girl working as a show rider of horses-an experience the author herself had in her teenage years. Lewis's second novel, The Second Suspect (1998), follows the struggles of a female police investigator trying to prove the guilt of a powerful and influential businessman responsible for the rape and murder of several young women. The third, posthumously published novel, Notice (2004), describes the experiences of a young prostitute, Nina and her involvement with a sadist and his wife. Her works explore aspects of American culture, such as the connections between power, drugs, sex, violence, love and justice. Through these themes, Heather Lewis draws the reader into questioning the nature of love and relationships, the character of human nature or motivation and, most challengingly, the boundary between pleasure and pain. Significantly, the novels present strong, yet vulnerable female characters offering an alternative to more typical American narrative constructions driven by male protagonists within male-dominated scenes.
Heather Lewis taught at the Writer's Voice and contributed to various anthologies of literature including Best Lesbian Erotica (1996, 1997), Once Upon a Time: Erotic Fairy Tales for Women (1996), and A Woman Like That: Lesbian and Bisexual Writers Tell Their Coming Out Stories (1999). The collection also includes work by Allan Gurganus, Dale Peck, Mike Corrigan, Margaret Au, as well as shorter pieces by Sarah Schulman, Meg Daly, and others. Heather Lewis returned to New York in the fall of 2001, after a year in Arizona. She ended her life in May of 2002, in New York.
Sources:
Memorial service program: St. Mark's Church, New York, NY, June 12, 2002.
"Pain and Perfection" (Anonymous). The Advocate; Los Angeles, June 11, 2002.
Scope and Content Note
The Heather Lewis Papers include materials relating to Heather Lewis's career as an author. The materials include journals, photographs and correspondence as well as manuscripts and research. In addition the collection contains financial documents and materials related to the publishing of her novels. The materials span 1965-2002, however the bulk of the materials are from the 1980s and 1990s.
Series I: Journals contains Heather Lewis's personal journals. These materials are arranged chronologically.
Series II: Author Files is divided into two subseries. Subseries A includes Heather Lewis's author information such as literary press and event information. This series only includes information not associated with her books. For publicity about Heather Lewis's novels please see Series II, III and IV. Subseries B contains information on other authors and artists including event publicity as well as art and literary pieces. These materials are arranged alphabetically by the author or artist's last name.
Series III: House Rules is divided into five subseries. Subseries A includes manuscripts for Gambler's Choice, which was an early draft form of House Rules. Subseries B contains manuscripts for Sixty-Forty, another early title for House Rules. Subseries C includes House Rules manuscripts and drafts. Subseries C holds publishing information for the novel House Rules. Finally, Subseries E includes publicity information. Materials are arranged alphabetically.
Series IV: The Second Suspect contains materials related to the writing and publication of Heather Lewis's second novel. The series is divided into three subseries. Subseries A includes manuscripts and drafts. Subseries B contains publication materials. Subseries C includes publicity materials such as reviews and advertisements. Materials are arranged alphabetically.
Series V: Notice contains manuscript materials related to Heather Lewis's novel Notice. Lewis wrote this book after House Rules but could not find a publisher. Notice was published posthumously by Serpent's Tail in 2004.
Series VI: Other Writing includes Heather Lewis's other writing projects and is broken into five subseries. Subseries A contains short stories. Subseries B includes Lewis's writing from Sarah Lawrence College, particularly research papers. Subseries C contains poetry. Subseries D includes essays Lewis wrote as an adult and public letters. Subseries E: Miscellaneous includes a short paper on Martin Luther King Jr. from an unknown time period and chapters from a possible fourth novel featuring Detective Reese. These materials are in chronological order where possible. Remaining materials are in alphabetical order.
Series VII: Personal Correspondence and Biographical Materials is broken into four subseries. Subseries A contains letters from Heather Lewis organized alphabetically by the last name of the addressee. Subseries B contains letters to Heather Lewis where the first and last name of the sender is known. These materials are in alphabetical order by the sender's last name. Subseries C contains letters to Heather Lewis from senders who only included their first name. Materials are in alphabetical order. Subseries D includes letters to other people from other people, for example a letter to Allen Gurganus from Malaga Baldi. Finally, Subseries E includes biographical materials related to Heather Lewis's life. Again, these materials are in alphabetical order by recipient's last name.
Series VIII: Administrative Materials is broken into eleven subseries. Subseries A contains contracts for books and contributions arranged in chronological order.Subseries B includes royalty statements arranged in chronological order. Subseries C includes author photographs, some of Heather Lewis and some of other authors arranged alphabetically. Subseries D contains tax information arranged chronologically. Subseries E includes accounting, bills, and statements from credit card companies, banks and other financial institutions. These materials are arranged chronolocially. Subseries F holds administrative correspondence including letters from publishers, agents, and fans. These materials are arranged alphabetically. Subseries G incorporates calendars and contacts such as day planners, business cards and phone lists. The subseries is arranged in chronological order. Subseries H includes resumes, applications, and calls for papers arranged in alphabetical order. Subseries I holds materials related to Lewis's work instructing writing workshops. Materials are arranged chronologically. Subseries J includes promotional and journalistic materials on publishers arranged alphabetically. Suberies K holds miscellaneous items.
Series IX: Research includes two subseries. Subseries A contains notes. Subseries B contains subject files organized in alphabetical order.
Series X: Images includes three subseries. Subseries A: photographs, some with matching negatives includes candid, personal photographs of family, events, landscapes and friends. Where possible, the photographs and negatives are matched. These materials are arranged chronologically where possible, remaining materials are organized alphabetically. Subseries B: Unmatched Negatives holds negatives for which we have no prints. These materials are arranged alphabetically by content. Subseries C: Other Images contains an unsigned drawing.
Series XI: Juvenilia contains materials from Heather Lewis's childhood including yearbooks, school writing journals and children's literature. Materials are arranged chronologically where possible.
Series XII: Printed Material includes printed materials such as film posters, tourism pamphlets, maps and owner's manuals. Materials are arranged alphabetically.
Series XIII: Objects and Artifacts includes objects such as a trophy, library card, and pen. All of these items are located in Box 13 except the red leather datebook
Series XIV: Media contains two subseries. Subseries A includes 3.5 inch floppy disks. Subseries B includes all other media including 5.25 inch floppy disks, compact disks and Heather Lewis's laptop computer.
Oversize: there is one box of oversize materials at the end of the collection containing oversize materials from each of the series.
Arrangement
The collection consists of fourteen series.
The material is arranged both chronologically and alphabetically.
Series I: Journals
Series II: Author and Artist Files
Series III: House Rules
Series IV: Second Suspect
Series V: Notice
Series VI: Other Writing
Series VII: Personal Correspondence and Biographical Material
Series VIII: Administrative Materials
Series IX: Research
Series X: Images
Series XI: Juvenilia
Series XII: Printed Materials
Series XIII: Objects and Artifacts
Series IV: Media
Oversize - Series I: Journals
Oversize - Series III.E: House Rules - Publicity Materials
Oversize - Series IV.A: Second Suspect - Manuscripts
Oversize - Series VI.D: Other Writing - Essays, Letters
Oversize - Series VIII.F: Administrative Materials - Administrative Correspondence
Oversize - Series IX.B: Research - Subject Files
Oversize - Series X.A: Images - Photographs
Oversize - Series X.C: Images - Other Images
Oversize - Series XII: Printed Materials
Related Material at Fales Library and Special Collections
Serpent's Tail/ High Risk Books Archive
Separated Material
The following items have been removed from The Heather Lewis Papers and moved to the Fales Library's Downtown Book Collection. The items have been catalogued individually in Bobcat, NYU's online catalog.
Lewis, Heather. De Regels Van Het Spel [House Rules] Uitgeverij Anthos, Amsterdam. 1997.
Lewis, Heather. Drugi Podejrzany [The Second Suspect] Warszawa, 2001.
Lewis, Heather. Drugi Podejrzany [The Second Suspect] Warszawa, 2000.
Lewis, Heather. The Second Suspect. London: Piatkus, 1998.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Audiovisual and born-digital materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers.
Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Programs (documents); Laptop computers.; Teenage girls |v Fiction.; New York (N.Y.); Financial records; Lesbians |x Fiction.; Manuscripts for publication.; Notes.; Floppy disks.; Journals.; Scripts (documents); New York (N.Y.) |v Fiction.; Photographs.; School yearbooks.; Doubleday Publishers; Gurganus, Allan, 1947-; OutWrite; Lewis, Heather; Rower, Ann, 1938-; Martin Secker Ltd.; Writer's Voice; Serpent's Tail (Firm)
- Series I: Journals, 63487
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains Heather Lewis's personal journals arranged chronologically.
  - Journal, July 23, 1976-Fall 1980. Includes poetry and class notes., 1976-1980; 63566 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Inserts from journal, July 23, 1976-Fall 1980. Poetry, 1976-1980; 63565 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Journal, October 24, 1977-December 7, 1979. Includes photographs, personal entries, quotes, autographs, letters, paintings and drawings., 1977-1979; 63564 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Inserts from front and back covers of journal, October 24, 1977-December 7, 1979. Letters, photograph., 1977-1979; 63563 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Journal, includes photographs, personal entries, pressed leaves, poetry., 1978-1980; 63562 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Journal, Summer 1978-Jan. 8, 1980. Poems., 1978-1980; 63561 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Journal, Fall 1978-March 30, 1981. Poems., 1978-1980; 63560 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Journal, December 1978-April 1, 1981. Writing, with annotations., 1978-1981; 63559 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Inserts from back cover of writing journal, December 1978-April 1, 1981., 1978-1981; 63558 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Journal, January 2, 1979-December 15, 1979. Therapy journal., 63557 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Journal, September 21,1979-December 13,1979. Personal entries., 63556 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Journal, October 3, 1979-October 30, 1979. Dialogues, 63555 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Journal, November 16, 1979-December 15, 1979. Personal entries, 63554 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Journal, December 3, 1979- November 5, 1980. Poetry., 63553 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Inserts from poetry journal December 3, 1979-November 5, 1980. Found in back cover., 1979-1980; 63552 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Journal, December 26, 1979-March 1, 1980. Personal entries, 1979-1980; 63551 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Journal, begins April 13, 1980. Poetry and personal entries., 63550 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Journal, begins August 1982. Poetry, letters, personal entries., 63549 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Inserts from journal, begins August 1982. Poems, 63548 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Journal, October 13, 1982-November 8, 1982. Poetry, 63547 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Journal, July 22, 1985-December 13, 1985. Personal entries., 63546 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Journal, begins July 7, 1986. Poetry, notes., 63545 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Journal, January 23, 1987-May 16, 1987. Personal entries., 63544 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Journal, May 22, 1987-February 21, 1988. Personal entries., 1987-1988; 63543 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Journal, February 28, 1988-January 4, 1992. Personal entries., 1988-1992; 63542 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Journal, July 1988-June 1989. Personal entries, clippings., 1988-1989; 63541 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Journal June 1989-April 1990. Personal entries, 1989-1990; 63540 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Journal, June 1989-November 1991. Career and spiritual entries., 1989-1991; 63539 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Journal, September 1990-May 1992. Personal entries., 1990-1992; 63538 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Journal, December 1990-January 1992. Personal entries., 1990-1992; 63537 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Journal, ca. 1991. Writing schedule, encouragement, plans., 63536 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Journal, January 1992-August 1992. Gratitude, personal entries., 63535 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Journal, August -September 1992. Gratitude and personal entries., 63534 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Journal, September 1992- January 1993. Personal entries., 1992-1993; 63533 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Journal, January-February 1993. Personal entries., 63532 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Journal, April-July 1993., 63531 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Journal, July-September 1993. Personal entries., 63530 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Journal, September 1993-February 1994. Personal entries., 1993-1994; 63529 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Journal, beginning November 30, 1993. Personal notes, jottings., 63528 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Journal, December 1993-1994. Personal entries., 63527 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Journal, begins February 7, 1994. Personal entries., 63526 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Journal, July 1994-September 1994. Personal entries., 63525 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Journal, August-November 1994. Personal entries., 63524 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Journal, November 1994-January 1995. Personal entries., 1994-1995; 63523 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Journal, January 1995-April 1995. Personal entries., 63522 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Journal, April-May 1995. Personal entries., 63521 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Journal, April-June 1995. Personal entries., 63520 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Journal, June 1995. Personal entries., 63519 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Journal, June-August 1995. Personal entries., 63518 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Journal, August-September 1995. Personal entries., 63517 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Journal, September-October 1995., 63516 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Journal, October-November 1995., 63515 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Journal, November 1995. personal entries., 63514 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Journal, November -December 1995., 63513 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Journal, December 6, 1995-January 1, 1996. Personal entries, 1995-1996; 63512 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Journal, January 1-February 1, 1996. Personal entries., 63511 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Journal, February 1-March 10, 1996. Personal entries., 63510 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Journal, March 10, 1996. Single personal entry., 63509 (Box 4, Folder 58)
  - Journal, March 11-July 2, 1996. Personal entries., 63508 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Journal, March 12-April 10, 1996., 63507 (Box 4, Folder 60)
  - Journal, April 10-May 7, 1996. Personal entries., 63506 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Journal, May 4-June 2, 1996. Personal entries., 63505 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Journal, June-July 1996. Personal entries., 63504 (Box 4B, Folder 63)
  - Journal, July-August 1996. Personal entries., 63503 (Box 4B, Folder 64)
  - Journal, August-September 1996. Personal entries., 63502 (Box 4B, Folder 65)
  - Journal, September-November 1996. Personal entries., 63501 (Box 4B, Folder 66)
  - Journal, November 1996-January 1997. Personal entries., 1996-1997; 63500 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Journal, June-July. Poems and personal entries., undated; 63499 (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Journal, poems and personal entries., undated; 63498 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Journal, poems and insert., undated; 63497 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Journal, poems, undated; 63496 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Journal, Dialogues and affirmations., undated; 63495 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Journal, Dialogues and affirmations., undated; 63494 (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Journal, Dialogues and affirmations., undated; 63493 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Journal, Dialogues and affirmations., undated; 63492 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Journal, Affirmations., undated; 63491 (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Journal, Poems, personal entries., undated; 63490 (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Inserts from journal [series 1, box 5, folder 77], undated; 63489 (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Journal, Affirmations., undated; 63488 (Box 5, Folder 79)
- Series II: Author and Artist Files, 63450
  This series contains artist and author files. Subseries A is devoted to Heather Lewis' career, particularly literary events featuring her writing but not connected to a specific book project. Subseries B contains other author and artists' biographical information, writing and opening invitations.
  - Subseries A: Heather Lewis, 63479
    - Literary Events, 1989, 63486 (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - Literary Events, 1991., 63485 (Box 5, Folder 81)
    - Literary Events, 1992., 63484 (Box 5, Folder 82)
    - Literary Events, 1994., 63483 (Box 5, Folder 83)
    - Literary Events, 1995., 63482 (Box 5, Folder 84)
    - Literary Events, undated; 63481 (Box 5, Folder 85)
    - Unspecified acceptance and thank you speech., undated; 63480 (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - Subseries B: Other Authors and Artists, 63451
    - Alampi, Andrea, undated; 63478 (Box 5, Folder 87)
    - Ameen, Mark., 1991-1992; 63477 (Box 5, Folder 88)
    - Ameen, Mark. "Zombie Juice: a novel", undated; 63476 (Box 5, Folder 89)
    - Baldi, Malaga. Article also mentions House Rules., 1994; 63475 (Box 5, Folder 90)
    - Cooper, Jane., undated; 63474 (Box 5, Folder 91)
    - Corrigan, Mike and Margaret Au. "Frank Blunt's Driving Bits", undated; 63473 (Box 5, Folder 92)
    - Daly, Meg., undated; 63472 (Box 5, Folder 93)
    - Epes, Maria., 1996; 63471 (Box 5, Folder 94)
    - Gurbach, Marty., undated; 63470 (Box 5, Folder 95)
    - Gurganus, Allan, 1989-1994; 63469 (Box 5, Folder 96)
    - Gurganus, Allan. "He's One, Too: Being a Chronicle of Sexual Liberation, my own.", undated; 63468 (Box 5, Folder 97)
    - Gurganus, Allan. "The Mortician Confesses", undated; 63467 (Box 5, Folder 98)
    - Goles, Bea., undated; 63466 (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - Harris, E. Lynn, undated; 63465 (Box 5, Folder 100)
    - Keller, Susan., undated; 63464 (Box 5, Folder 101)
    - Kwok, Kary Ka-Che., 1994-1995; 63463 (Box 5, Folder 102)
    - Larkin, Joan., undated; 63462 (Box 5, Folder 103)
    - McPherson, Sandra., undated; 63461 (Box 5, Folder 104)
    - Morrison, Toni., 1994; 63460 (Box 5, Folder 105)
    - Pakula, Alan J., 1999; 63459 (Box 5, Folder 106)
    - Peck, Dale. "Now it's time to say goodbye.", undated; 63458 (Box 6, Folder 107)
    - Peck, Dale. "Now it's time to say goodbye.", undated; 63457 (Box 6, Folder 108)
    - Peck, Dale. "Now it's time to say goodbye.", undated; 63456 (Box 6, Folder 109)
    - Perkins, Jane., 1996; 63455 (Box 6, Folder 110)
    - Rower, Ann., undated; 63454 (Box 6, Folder 111)
    - Schulman, Sarah, 1996; 63453 (Box 6, Folder 112)
    - Unger, Barbara., undated; 63452 (Box 5, Folder 113)
- Series III: House Rules, 63403
  This series contains manuscripts, and publishing and publicity materials related to Heather Lewis's first novel, House Rules. It is important to note that this project underwent several name changes. Initially Lewis called the project "Gambler's Choice" and "60-40" before changing the novel's title to "House Rules". With this in mind, the series is divided into five subseries. Subseries A consists of "Gambler's Choice" manuscripts. Subseries B includes "Sixty-Forty" manuscripts and plot synoposis. Subseries C includes "House Rules" manuscripts, outlines and summaries. Subseries D contains publishing information such as cover art. Subseries E includes publicity materials including advertisements, interviews and book reviews. Materials are organized alphabetically in each subseries.
  - Subseries A: Gambler's Choice Manuscript, 63447
    - "Gambler's Choice", undated; 63449 (Box 6, Folder 114)
    - To do list "fixing" Gambler's Choice, uses all three titles: Gambler's Choice, 60-40 and House Rules., undated; 63448 (Box 6, Folder 115)
  - Subseries B: "Sixty-Forty" Manuscript, 63443
    - Plot synopsis "Sixty-Forty" or "House Rules", undated; 63446 (Box 6, Folder 116)
    - "Sixty-Forty Current" Draft with annotations., undated; 63445 (Box 6, Folder 117)
    - "60-40 - Early Drafts" with annotations and drawings, undated; 63444 (Box 6, Folder 118)
  - Subseries C: House Rules Manuscripts, 63422
    - Acknowledgements, undated; 63442 (Box 6, Folder 119)
    - "Allan's Comments", undated; 63441 (Box 6, Folder 120)
    - Draft, Chapter 3, undated; 63440 (Box 6, Folder 121)
    - House Rules Draft, chapter 5, with annotations., undated; 63439 (Box 6, Folder 122)
    - House Rules Draft. Chapter 20, with annotations., undated; 63438 (Box 6, Folder 123)
    - House Rules Draft, Chapter 21 with annotations., undated; 63437 (Box 6, Folder 124)
    - House Rules Draft, Chapter 32 with annotations, undated; 63436 (Box 6, Folder 125)
    - House Rules Draft, unlabeled, undated; 63435 (Box 6, Folder 126)
    - House Rules draft, unlabeled, undated; 63434 (Box 6, Folder 127)
    - House Rules draft, assorted chapters and pages, includes Road Map., undated; 63433 (Box 6, Folder 128)
    - House Rules draft, unlabeled fragments., undated; 63432 (Box 6, Folder 129)
    - House Rules draft, unlabeled chapter., undated; 63431 (Box 6, Folder 130)
    - House Rules "Early Drafts" with annotations., undated; 63430 (Box 6, Folder 131)
    - House Rules draft, fragments., undated; 63429 (Box 6, Folder 132)
    - House Rules draft fragments., undated; 63428 (Box 6, Folder 133)
    - House Rules draft fragment, undated; 63427 (Box 6, Folder 134)
    - House Rules draft fragment, undated; 63426 (Box 6, Folder 135)
    - House Rules draft fragment, undated; 63425 (Box 6, Folder 136)
    - House Rules Road Maps, ca. 1991-1992; 63424 (Box 6, Folder 137)
    - House Rules, summary, undated; 63423 (Box 6, Folder 138)